Guide to the Margaret Hodges Papers, 1911-2006 SC.1990.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Margaret Hodges Papers
1911-2006
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hodges, Margaret
SC.1990.03
22 Linear Feet (46 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize)
The Margaret Hodges Papers document her career as storyteller, librarian, author, teacher, and advocate for childhood studies. The collection includes drafts, correspondence, teaching materials, storytelling scripts, photographs, and media.
Acquisition Information
Multiple donations made by Hodges over the course of many years while teaching at the University of Pittsburgh Library School.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection consists of 45 manuscript boxes and one oversize box and includes correspondence, interviews, research for and drafts of books, teaching materials, photographs, media, and other materials that document Margaret Hodges' work as an author and scholar of children's literature.
Biography/History
Sarah Margaret Hodges was born in Indianapolis, Indiana, in 1911. Her mother, Anna Marie Moore, died six months after Margaret was born. An older cousin cared for the household which included Margaret, her brother, father and grandfather. Both her father and the Second Presbyterian Church Sunday School were instrumental in introducing to her the art of storytelling.
During her sophomore year at Tudor Hall, a prep school for girls, Hodges was introduced to Fletcher Hodges, who she would marry in 1932. She attended Vassar College where she studied English and theatre and graduated with honors in 1932. In 1937, Margaret and Fletcher moved to Pittsburgh and he became curator at the Stephen Foster Memorial.
After raising three children, Hodges volunteered at the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh. During this time she also wrote scripts for a radio program called "The Children's Bookshelf" and in 1953, she was asked to take a paid position as a storyteller for a radio program called "Let's Tell a Story." In 1964, the program became "Tell Me a Story", a nationally broadcast television program on Pittsburgh's WQED-TV.
During this time, Hodges applied for a scholarship that would enable her to earn a Master's degree in Library Science at the Carnegie Institute of Technology, now Carnegie Mellon University. Two years later, in 1958, her first book, One Little Drum, was published by Follett Publishing Company.
Hodges continued to work at the Carnegie Library until 1964, when she left to join the Head Start program as Story Specialist for Pittsburgh Public Schools. At the same time, Dr. Harold Lancour, the Dean of the University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Library and Information Science, asked Hodges to teach a course in storytelling which lead to her eventually teaching all courses in children's services. In 1978, she retired as professor emeritus from the University of Pittsburgh.
One of Hodge's greatest contribtions was the development of Elizabeth Nesbitt Children's Book Collection. While attending the Carnegie Institute, Hodges studied under storyteller and teacher, Elizabeth Nesbitt, an experence that influenced Hodges for the rest of her life. She was able to pay tribute to her influential teacher when in 1976 she began developing the Elizabeth Nesbitt Room at the University of Pittsburgh library school. The Nesbitt Children's Book Collection, now housed at the University of Pittsburgh Archives and Special Collections, features a range of materials including chapbooks, toy books, boardbooks, and juvenile periodicals. She continued to curate and support this collection until her death in December of 2005.
During her career, Hodges also wrote and illustrated more than 60 books, including Caldecott winner St. George and the Dragon.
Custodial History
This collection was donated to and housed at the Elizabeth Nesbitt Room at the University of Pittsburgh School of Information Science Library until its closure in 2012, when the materials were transferred to Special Collections.
Related Material
Margaret Hodges also made manuscript donations to the following repositories: University of Oregon; University of Minnesota, Kerlan Collection; and the University of Southern Mississippi, DeGrummond Collection.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Arrangement
The papers are organized according to the following series:
Series I: Personal Papers
Series II: Radio and TV Storytelling
Series III: University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Library and Information Sciences (GSLIS)
Series IV: Correspondence
Series V: Articles
Series VI: Children's Books
Series VII: Other Writing
Series VIII: Media
Series IX: Oversize
Previous Citation
Maragaret Hodges Collection, 1911-2006, SC.1990.03, University of Pittsburgh Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Women authors, American -- 20th century; Illustrators -- United States -- Juvenile literature; Children's stories, American; Children's books -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Authors, American -- 20th century; University of Pittsburgh. School of Library and Information Science; Hodges, Margaret
- Personal Papers, 1911-2006; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Personal materials related to Hodges' childhood, education, professional life, and her many awards and honors, including the founding of the Elizabeth Nesbitt room. Papers from close friends and family are included in this series as well.
  - Autobiography, 1988-1992; 1.
    - Short Autobiography (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correpondence, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Diaries, 1977-1988; 2.
    - Trip to England and Description of Early Life, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Greece and England, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hong Kong, China, Japan, Hawaii, Bermuda, England, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - New Zealand, Australia, Tahiti, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Spain, Portugal; Epic Backgrounds II and 17th Century Literature, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Education, 1932-2000; 3.
    - Carnegie Library School, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Vassar College, 1932-2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Vassar College, 50th Reunion, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - University of Pittsburgh, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memberships, 1967-1992; 4.
    - Memberships, 1967-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Judging, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Boards and Committees, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Events, 1971-1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Appearences and Lectures, 1965-1994; 5.
    - Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, Storytelling Festival, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Mt. Aloysius of Pittsburgh, Storytelling Festival, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Edinboro State College, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - PA Library Association South West Chapter; WQED Lyceum, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - River City Library, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Frick Fine Arts, Pitt,The Book Goes Public 1100-1550, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Drexel University, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - The Elizabeth Nesbitt Room 15th Anniversary Celebration,The Inside Story of the Elizabeth Nesbitt Room, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - The Elizabeth Nesbitt Room 15th Anniversary Celebration, Guestbook, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Children's Literature Association, Hattiesburg, PA; 14th Annual Storytelling Workshop, University of Washington, WA, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Japan Association of Greater Pittsburgh, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Chla, the Image of the Child, the 18th Annual International Conference of Children's Literature Association Hattiesburgh, Mississippi; College Club of Pittsburgh, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Women's International Club, Pitt; Marion County PL, IN; Books for Children and Youth, Pitt; Stevenson Library, Lock Haven, PA, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Invitations to Speak and Miscellaneous Speeches, 1973-circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Keyser HS Mineral County, WV, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Literary Awards, 1970-2004; 6.
    - Indiana Authors' Day Award, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Indiana Authors' Day Award, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Outstanding PA Author Award, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Daughter of Mark Twain Award, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Keystone to Reading Book Award, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - First Annual Pennbook Award, PA Center for the Book, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Junior League of Pittsburgh Literacy Award, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Hope Dean Award, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Distinguished Alumna Awards, 1976-1992; 7.
    - University of Pittsburgh and Carnegie Library School, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - University of Pittsburgh, Bicentennial Medallion of Distinction, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Park Tudor School, IN, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous Awards, 1970-2001; 8.
    - Margaret Hodges Day, University of Pittsburgh, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Margaret Hodges Day, Evansville, IN, Including VHS, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Distinguished Daughters of Pennsylvania, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Awards, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Awarded Scholarships and Grants, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Award Nominations, 1999-2001 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Honors, 1974-2003; 9.
    - Retirement From the University of Pittsburgh, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Margaret Hodges Scholarship, Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Margaret Hodges Scholarship, Donations, 1989-2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Peggy Hodges Birthday at Frick Fine Arts VHS, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Fletcher Hodges, Jr. Curatorship at the Center for American Music (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Point Park College Doctor of Humane Letters Honorary Degree, Correspondence, Articles, and Commencement Address, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Storytellers Unlimited Honors and Guest Book, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Storytellers Unlimited Scrapbook, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Published Works and Articles About, 1964-2006; 10.
    - Published Works About Hodges, circa 1970-2002 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Articles About Hodges, 1964-1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Obituaries and Memorials, 2005-2006 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript Donations, 1966-1992; 11.
    - University of Oregon, 1972-1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - University of Minnesota, Kerlan Collection, 1967-1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - University of Southern Mississippi, DeGrummond Collection, 1966-1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Family and Associate Papers, 1940-2006; 12.
    - Cover for Fletcher Hodges, Jr.'s Newsletter (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Letter to Sarah Margaret From Father, Describing Family History, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Eulogy for Brother John and Poem for Hodges' Anniversary (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Moore Coat of Arms (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Fletcher Hodges, Jr., Burial Service Music and Program, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Trina Schart Hyman Memorial Papers (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Katharine Briggs Papers (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, 1911-2005; 13.
    - Posed, Headshots, and Wedding, 1932-2002 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Family, Childhood and Adolescence, 1901-1939 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Family, 1946-1966, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Portraits (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Storytellers Unlimited, April 9, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous (includes photos with Katharine Briggs), 1977-1999 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Scanned, Created by Digital Research Library, University Library System, University of Pittsburgh, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Radio and TV Storytelling, 1945-1999; II.
  Hodges voluntarily wrote scripts for the radio program, "The Children's Bookshelf," until 1953 when she was asked by the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh to take a paid position as a storyteller for a radio program called "Let's Tell a Story." Later, in 1964, the radio program became "Tell Me a Story", a nationally broadcast television program on Pittsburgh's WQED-TV.
  Each subseries contains radio scripts, program guides, and related materials.
  An outline of episodes for Let's Tell A Story was created by one of the student processors, Katharine Pigliacelli, and is available upon request.
  - The Children's Bookshelf, Radio Scripts and Programs, 1946-1952 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - The Children's Bookshelf, Article and Speech, 1945-circa 1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Fun With Books, Program List, Radio Script for Kidnapped, Teacher's Manual, circa 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Book Parade, Radio Script (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Let's Tell a Story, 1953-1961; 1.
    - 9/21/1953-1/25/1954 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 2/1/1954-6/9/1954 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - 9/20/1954-1/31/1955 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
    - 2/2/1955-6/1/1955 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 9/26/1955-2/1/1956 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 2/6/1956-6/20/1956 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 9/24/1956-1/30/1957 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 2/4/1957-6/19/1957 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 6/23/1957-1/29/1958 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 2/3/1958-6/18/1958 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 9/22/1958-1/28/1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 2/2/1959-6/17/1959 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 9/28/1959-2/8/1960 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 2/15/1960-6/20/1960 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 9/26/1960-1/30/1961 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 2/13/1961-12/19/1961 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - The Wonderful Tar-Baby (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Articles and Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Research Photos, the Steel Industry and Joe Magaree (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Tell Me A Story, 1953-1999; 2.
    - Radio Scripts (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Schedules, Promotional Materials, and Teaching Manuals, 1953-1971 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1999 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1953-1999 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Photographs and Copied Photographs, 1953-1970 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- University of Pittsburgh, Graduate School of Library and Information Sciences (GSLIS), 1960-2005; III.
  In 1964, the Dean of the University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Library and Information Science, asked Mrs. Hodges to teach a course in storytelling, which eventually led to her teaching all of the courses in children's services. She retired as a professor emerita in 1978.
  This series contains materials related to her various courses including syllabi, assigments, and teaching resources.
  - Administrative Activities, 1963-2004; 1.
    - Vitae, 1963, 1968-2004 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence Regarding Vitae, 1967-1980 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Guest Lecturer Information, Walter Oakeshott and Katharine Briggs, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - GSLIS Christmas Party, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Elizabeth Nesbitt Room, Promotion and Gifts, 1978-2005 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Nomination of Dr. Robert B. Hinman for Chancellor's Distinguished Teaching Award, Research and Typescript, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - LIS 222: Materials for Children, 1960-1985; 2.
    - Course Content, 1970-1977
      - Syllabus and Schedule, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Assignments, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Introduction (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Unit II - Types of Children's Books, Non-Fiction (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Unit III - Types of Children's Books, Fiction (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Unit IV - A Basic Book Collection (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Unit V - Review Media in Selection of Children's Materials (Box 8, Folder 13)
      - Unit VI - The Children's Book World (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - Unit VII - The Multi-Media Approach to Children's Literature (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - Unit VIII - Innovative Programs and the Children's Room (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - Unit IX - Community Relations and the Children's Room; Unit X - The Children's Librarian, A Personal Approach (Box 8, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence Regarding Class Activities and Speakers, 1970-1977 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Reference Sources, 1960-1985
      - Book Awards and Honors, 1967-1979 (Box 8, Folder 19)
      - Book Selection Aids, 1968-1977 (Box 8, Folder 20)
      - Children's Literature, 1960-1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Classics, circa 1973 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Fantasy, 1970-1975 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Important Books for Children, Carnegie Public Library, 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Books of International Interest, Pamphlets, 1961-1974 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Books of International Interest, Articles, 1966-1976 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Picture Books, 1969-1977 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Poetry, Verse, Songs, 1965-1985 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Reluctant Readers, 1966-1975 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - LIS 223: Materials for Young Adults, 1968-1977; 3.
    - Course Content
      - Syllabus, 1969-1975 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence Regarding Class Activities and Speakers, 1971-1974 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Reference Sources, 1968-1977
      - Books as Therapy, 1968-1977 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Censorship and Controversial Books, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Creating an Outreach Program, Guidelines and Examples, Part 1, 1968-1977 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Creating an Outreach Program, Guidelines and Examples, Part 2, 1968-1977 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Introduction to Literature, 1968-1977 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Young Adult Books, 1971-1974 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Puppetry and Puppet Scripts, 1970-1976
      - Puppets and Puppeteering, 1970-1975 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Alice in Wonderland (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - The Brementown Musicians (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Cinderella (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - The Clever Turtle (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Little Red Riding Hood (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Mr. Rabbit and Mr. Bear (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - The Pied Piper of Hamelin (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Racketty, Packetty House, Adapted by Margaret Hodges (Box 10, Folder 12)
      - Rumplestiltskin (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Three Billy Goats Gruff (Box 10, Folder 14)
      - The Three Wishes (Box 10, Folder 15)
      - Toad of Toad Hall (Box 10, Folder 16)
      - Puppet Play Photographs, 1970-1976 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - LIS 224: History of Children's Literature, 1967-1984; 4.
    - Course Content
      - Syllabus, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence Regarding Class Activities and Speakers, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Reference Sources, 1967-1984
      - General Historical Survey and Traditional Literature, circa 1975 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Location of Books in Closed Stacks, Rare Book Resources, circa 1975 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Location of Books in Closed Stacks, Articles, 1968-1981 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Anglo-Saxon Period (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - The Feudal Age, circa 1970 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Tudor and Renaissance (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - 17th Century, 1970, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - 18th Century, Including French Fairytales, 1973-1975 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Early 19th Century, 1967-1975 (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - Early American Literature, 1974-1980 (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Illustrators, 1974-1980 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Early and Mid-Victorian Literature, 1976-1984 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Late 19th Century English American Authors, 1972-1984 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Course Performances, 1974
      - Alice in Wonderland (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Bottom the Actor, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Noah's Flood (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Sir Gawain and the Green Knight, with Music (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - The Toad of Toad Hall (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - A Birthday Tribute to Lewis Carroll, Photographs (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - LIS 226: Storytelling, 1965-1977; 5.
    - Course Content
      - Syllabus, 1971-1976 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence Regarding Class Activities, 1973-1974 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Reference Sources, 1965-1977
      - Introduction to Storytelling, 1965-1975 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Pre-School Story Hour, 1968-1974 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Myths, 1972-1977 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Epics, circa 1970 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - LIS 227: Seminar in Folklore, 1967-1991; 6.
    - Course Content, 1973-1986
      - Syllabus, 1975-1980 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - Correspondence, 1973-1980 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Folklore Institute, Indiana University, 1973-1974 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - Folklore and Mythology, Harvard University, circa 1974 (Box 12, Folder 18)
      - 6th International Folklore Congress, Helsinki, Finland, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - The Mythic Image: Folklore and Libraries, University of Minnesota, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Conference on Research in Folkloristic Materials, Chapel Hill, NC, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Other Folklore Conferences: American Folklore Society, Festival of American Folklife, International Society for Folk-Narrative Research, 1976-1980 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Pittsburgh Ethnic Groups and Festivals, Including Nationality Rooms, 1973-1986 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Joseph Campbell Interview, circa 1980 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Reference Sources, 1967-1991
      - General Reference Material About Folklore, 1974-1980 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Ethnic Folklore (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Ethnic Folklore, Resources, 1967-1982 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Celtic Folkflore, 1971-1974 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Fairytales, 1970-1991 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Workshop, Current Trends in Early Childhood Development and Education, 1965-1977; 7.
    - Reports and Brochures, 1974-1976 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Library Services Reference Material, 1966-1977 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Library Services Reference Articles, 1975-1976 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Teaching Resources, 1971-1977; 8.
    - Songs (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Transparencies (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence Regarding Unspecified Class Activities and Speakers, 1971-1977 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Proposed Courses and Seminars, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1960-2005; IV.
  Personal and professional correspondence including correspondence with Fred Rogers, Trina Schart Hyman, and Katharine Briggs.
  - By Correspondent, 1.
    - From Katharine Briggs, 1974-2000 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - To Katharine Briggs, 1974-1979 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Editors, 1973-1996 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Elizabeth Nesbitt Room, 1977-1985 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - To and From Clifton Fadiman, 1977, 1997-1998 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - From Trina Schart Hyman, 1995-2003 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - National Storytelling League and Storytellers Unlimited, 1970-1979 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - From Fred Rogers, 1977-1996 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - By Date, 2.
    - 1960-1969 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - 1974 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - 1975 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - 1976 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - 1977 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1978 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 1979 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 1990-1999 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 2000-2005 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Articles, 1923-1985; V.
  Articles written by Hodges herself or in collaboration with others in the field of children's literature. Included are multiple drafts of articles in the series, including handwritten notes and corrections. Unpublished articles can also be found.
  - Published Articles, 1.
    - Three Charades-St. Nicholas, 1923 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Polly's Christmas-The Bell News (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Shawnty Green and Ulysses-Vassar Review, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Thumb on the Pulse-Junior League Lights, 1948 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Many Are Called -Junior League Lights, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - We Didn't Know We Had It In Us -Junior League Lights, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 6)